Albert Schweitzer Fellowship Records
Albert Schweitzer Fellowship Records
- Albert Schweitzer Fellowship Records
  - ASF programs and projects
    - Albert Schweitzer Centenary
      - Events, 1975 (Box 18)
      - Correspondence, 1974-1975 (Box 19)
      - Clippings, 1975 (Box 19)
      - Clippings scrapbooks, 1975 (Oversize 2)
      - Concert 1/14/75, 1974-1975 (Box 19)
      - Concert poster, 1975 (Oversize 3)
    - Leprosy Rehabilitation Center Proposal, 1971-1973 (Box 19)
    - Fund-raising activities
      - 1981-1982 (Box 19)
      - 1972-1974 (Box 19)
      - Howard A. Rusk, Consultant, 1980-1983 (Box 19)
      - Hospital Campaign
        - 1971-1974 (Box 19)
        - Board of Directors, 1972-1974 (Box 19)
        - White House correspondence, 1972-1974 (Box 19)
        - Edward W. Brooke Dinner, 1974 (Box 19)
        - Paul Dudley White Luncheon, 1972 (Box 19)
        - Harold L. Oram, Inc., 1971-1974 (Box 19)
        - Contributions, 1972-1974 (Box 20)
        - Direct mail appeals, 1972-1974 (Box 20)
        - Foundations, 1972-1974 (Box 20)
        - Donor Records, 1974 (Box 20)
    - Benefit concerts, 1954-1959; includes programs, correspondence and clippings (Box 20)
  - ASF publications
    - Correspondence, etc., 1982-1987 (Box 20)
    - ASF Courier
      - Correspondence, etc., 1979-1986; includes correspondence, clippings, article typescripts and manuscripts (Box 20)
      - Correspondence, etc., 1975-1977 (Box 20)
      - Printed material, 1959; 1974,; 1978-1987 (Box 20)
    - Writings
      - Homer Jack, Schweitzer and Nuclear War, 1984-1987 (Box 21)
      - John Impey, 1985 (Box 21)
      - Lee Ellerbrock, Reverence for Life, 1980 (Box 21)
      - Miscellaneous, 1975-1976 (Box 21)
        Includes writings by Alan Cameron, Luis Cueto Coll, Norman Cousins, David L. Dungan, Leo Fishbein, Erwin R. Jacobi, Hermann Mai, Hans Margolius, Rhena Schweitzer Miller, Harold Robles, Otto Spear, Herbert Spiegelberg
      - Albert Schweitzer, The Hospital at Lambarene during the War Years, 1939-1945, 1947; printed material (Box 21)
    - Special projects and awards, 1984-1986 (Box 21)
    - Videotapes: A Gift from Doctor Schweitzer, 1986; 2 cassettes (VHS and Beta) (Box 21)
    - Filmstrip: Erica Anderson Presents Albert Schweitzer, 1957-1965; includes filmstrip, script and presentation guide, correspondence, distribution records (Box 21)
- Albert Schweitzer Hospital
  - Communications
    - 1985-1987 (Box 21)
    - 1971-1984 (Box 22)
    - 1967-1970 (Box 23)
    - Annual meeting, 1983 (Box 23)
    - Organizational Review documents, 1982 (Box 23)
    - Financial reports, 1974-1975 (Box 23)
    - Correspondence, 1953-1962 (Box 23)
  - Medical reports
    - 1983-1987, includes French originals and English translations (Box 23)
    - 1973-1975, 1979-1982 (Box 23)
  - Publications
    - Miscellaneous, 1972-1981 (Box 23)
  - Hospital construction
    - Miscellaneous, 1975-1977; includes photographs, blueprints, financial records (Box 23)
  - U.S. A.I.D. Grant
    - Miscellaneous, 1973-1978 (Box 23)
  - Subject files
    - Lambarene Hospital after Albert Schweitzer, 1966-1986; clippings (Box 23)
    - Suppliers, 1958-1970 (Box 23)
    - Suppliers, 1958-1970 (Box 24)
    - Medical studies and evaluations, 1961-1967 (Box 24)
    - Gifts, clippings, 1956-1965 (Box 24)
    - Clara Palm Estate, 1955-1960 (Box 24)
    - Report of visit to hospital, 1947; clipping (Box 24)
- A.I.S.L.
  - Communications
    - 1979-1987 (Box 24)
    - 1973-1978 (Box 25)
    - 1967-1971 (Box 25)
    - 1963-1965 (Box 25)
    - 1950-1951, 1961-1962 (Box 25)
    - National Schweitzer Associations, 1947-1968; includes groups in Aruba, France, Germany, Great Britain, Holland, Korea, Sweden, Switzerland (Box 25)
  - Subject files
    - Schweitzer International Symposium, Cambridge, England, 1983; includes correspondence, schedules and announcements, conference papers (Box 25)
    - Schweitzer slide set, Netherlands, 1981 (Box 26)
    - Schweitzer Symposium, Deventer, Netherlands, 1978; includes program, published papers (Box 26)
    - Stamp project, 1960-1975; includes correspondence from 1960-81 with letters signed by Edward M. Kennedy, Robert F. Kennedy, and Jacob Javits, set of stamps from Liberia (Box 26)
    - Foundation Albert Schweitzer Prize, Netherlands, 1964-1969 (Box 26)
    - Albert Schweitzer College, Switzerland, 1954-1968 (Box 26)
    - Lambarene Hospital drawing (captions in French, German, English), 1948 (Box 26)
    - Schweitzer Sculpture, Netherlands, undated; photographs (Box 26)
  - Publications
    - Albert Schweitzer Bulletin (A.I.S.L., in German, English, French), 1976-1981 (Box 26)
    - Les Cahiers de l'Association Belge des Amis de Albert Schweitzer (Belgium), 1960-1965 (Box 26)
    - Cahiers Albert Schweitzer (France), 1962-1992 (Box 26)
    - Radiance (Glinsbach, France; English and French, 1981-1986 (Box 26)
    - Lettres de l'Hopital du Dr. Albert Schweitzer a Lambarene (France), 1930-1966 (Box 26)
    - French publications (in English and French), 1955-1986 (Box 26)
    - Rundbrief-- Albert-Schweitzer-Komite in der DDR (East Germany), 1963-1989 (Box 26)
    - Albert-Schweitzer-Komite in der DDR: Special Issues, 1975; 1980 (Box 26)
    - Rundbrief far alle Freunde von Albert Schweitzer (West Germany), 1984-1991 (Box 27)
    - Rundbrief far alle Freunde von Albert Schweitzer, 1956-1982; includes earlier titles: two series seem to combine during 1966-1970 (Box 27)
    - Ehrfurcht vor dem Leben, Gerhard Kahn (West Germany), 1985-1990 (Box 27)
    - West German publications, 1959-? (Box 27)
    - Dr. Schweitzer's Hospital Fund (Great Britain), 1929-1982 (Box 27)
    - British publications, 1960; 1975 (Box 27)
    - Albert Schweitzer Bulletin/Eerbied voor het Leven en nieuws uit Lambarene (Netherlands), 1956-1966; 1968-1991; 2 folders (Box 27)
    - Dutch publications, undated; includes set of photo-greeting cards (Box 27)
    - Circulo de Amigos de Albert Schweitzer, Boletin (Spain), 1981-1982 (Box 27)
    - Berichte aus Lambarene (Switzerland), 1953-1991 (Box 27)
    - Nouvelles de Lambarene (Switzerland), 1958-1972; 1983 (Box 27)
    - Briefe aus dem Lambarenespital (Switzerland), 1925-1954 (Box 27)
    - Swiss publications, 1955-1975 (Box 27)
    - Austrian, Polish, Swedish publications, 1967-1986 (Box 27)
- Albert Schweitzer Center
  - Communications
    - 1981-1987 (Box 28)
    - 1979 (Box 28)
    - 1977 (Box 28)
    - 1969-1971 (Box 28)
  - Publications
    - Miscellaneous, 1977-1993; includes issues of Reverence and A.S.F.H. Newsletter (Box 28)
- Schweitzer memorabilia
  - Albert Schweitzer documents
    - Letters, 1940-1965; includes original and photocopied letters, with many translations and annotations (Box 28)
    - Letters, undated (Box 28)
    - Correspondence chronology (Laura Person), undated (Box 28)
    - Article, "The U.N. Have No Right to Force Katanga to Pay the Congo", 1962-1963 (Box 28)
    - Miscellaneous writings, 1946-1962 (Box 28)
    - Writings on Nuclear Issues, 1958; 1961 (Box 28)
    - Sunday Worship at the Lambarene Hospital (German, French, English), 1931; 1958 (Box 28)
    - Statement, "A Declaration of Conscience", 1957 (Box 28)
    - Article, "Wie mein Lebenswerk entstand", 1957 (Box 28)
    - Lambarene Hospital drawings, autographed, 1956 (Box 28)
    - Nobel Prize Address, "Le Probleme de la Paix", 1954 (Box 28)
      See also Albert Schweitzer Fellowship Records: ASF office files: Subject files: Schweitzer Nobel Prize Address (Box 6) and Schweitzer-related materials: Clippings: Nobel Prize (Box 30)
    - Article, "Medicine in the Jungle", 1954 (Box 28)
    - Letter, engraved on print block (in box), November 26, 1952 (Box 28)
    - Speech, Humanity and Peace (German and English), 1951
    - Transcript from Radio Address, "L'Ethique du Respect de la Vie", 1951 (Box 28)
    - Article, "Der fur Bachs Werke fur Violine solo erforderte Geigenbogen", 1950 (Box 28)
    - Lecture, "Goethe: His Personality and Work", 1949 (Box 28)
    - Interview and sermon, 1947 (Box 28)
    - Tribute to Nathan Soderblom (English translation from Swedish), 1933 (Box 28)
    - Report of 1913 Arrival in Lambarene, 1914?; includes French typescript of entry from Schweitzer's journal, published in Journal des Missions Evangeliques (May, 1914) (Box 28)
    - Sermon (English translation), 1909? (Box 28)
    - On the Significance of Bach (German), 1905 (Box 28)
    - Last Meditation on Reverence for Life, undated (Box 28)
    - Ausgewahlte Werke, Tables of Contents, undated (Box 28)
    - Miscelleneous items by Schweitzer, See ASF Office Files: Subject Files, boxes 6-7, 9 and ASF Publications, box 21.
  - Helene Schweitzer documents
    - Clippings, 1950; 1957 (Box 29)
    - Correspondence, 1937-1956; includes lists and annotations compiled by Laura Person, particularly of correspondence between Helene and Emory and Myrta Ross (Box 29)
    - Article on Albert Schweitzer, 1949 (Box 29)
  - Schweitzer-related materials
    - Chronology for Albert Schweitzer, 1971 (Box 29)
    - Tributes and memorials, 1965-1966 (Box 29)
    - Evaluation of Schweitzer, Conor Cruise O'Brien, 1966 (Box 29)
    - Article, "Letters from Albert Schweitzer in the Colby College Library" / Julius Seelye Bixler, 1964 (Box 29)
    - Article, "Albert Schweitzer's Bach", 1960 (Box 29)
    - Color slides of Schweitzer, Lambarene, Gunsbach, 1960? (Box 29)
    - Erica Anderson's Albert Schweitzer Kalendar (picture calendar, German), 1959 (Box 29)
    - Pictures and photographs, 1948-1951; includes postcards of Lambarene, Colmar, and Gunsbach, photographs of Schweitzer in Gunsbach and Aspen (Box 29)
    - Articles and notes, 1933-1948 (Box 29)
    - Lambarene photos, Dr. Charles Joy, 1947 (Box 29)
      See also ASF Office Files: Correspondence: Joy, Charles R. (Box 4)
    - Copper cuts of Lambarene photos (in box), 1947?; 5 items (Box 29)
    - Photo, Dwight Eisenhower, with inscription for Albert Schweitzer, undated (Box 29)
    - Dictaphone cassette, marked "Lambarene", undated (Box 29)
    - Miscellaneous or undated (Box 29)
    - Clippings
      - Newspaper stories and interviews, 1946-1975 (Box 29)
      - English language articles, 1944-1968 (Box 29)
      - German language articles, 1945-1968 (Box 30)
      - French language articles, 1951-1965 (Box 30)
      - Scandinavian language articles, 1953-1959 (Box 30)
      - Obituaries for Albert Schweitzer, 1965-1966 (Box 30)
      - Hospital visitors, 1947-1963 (Box 30)
      - Awards for Schweitzer, 1955-1963; includes list compiled by Laura Person, with bibliographic notations (Box 30)
      - Languages other than English or German, 1954-1961 (Box 30)
      - Opposition to Nuclear Weapons Tests, 1954-1958 (Box 30)
      - Nobel Prize, 1952-1954 (Box 30)
        See also Schweitzer Memorabilia: Albert Schweitzer Documents: Nobel Prize Address for the original in French (Box 28) and Albert Schweitzer Fellowship Records: ASF office files: Subject files: Schweitzer Nobel Prize Address (Box 6)
      - Treuenfels Obituary Collection
        - International list of obituaries for Schweitzer, 1965(?) (Box 30)
        - Americas, 1965 (Box 30)
        - United States, 1965 (Box 30)
        - Asia and Africa, 1965 (Box 30)
        - Australia and New Zealand, 1965 (Box 30)
        - Europe, 1965 (Box 30)
        - France, 1965 (Box 30)
        - Germany, 1965 (Box 30)
        - Great Britain, 1965 (Box 30)
    - Printed matter
      - 1990-1992 (Box 31)
      - 1980-1989 (Box 31)
      - 1970-1979 (Box 31)
      - 1960-1969 (Box 31)
      - 1960-1969 (Box 32)
      - 1950-1959 (Box 32)
      - 1950-1959 (Box 33)
      - 1940-1949 (Box 33)
      - 1930-1939 (Box 33)
    - Publications by or about Albert Schweitzer, various languages and dates (Box 34)
      List of items:
      Albert Schweitzer, Decadência e Regeneracão da Cultura 1959
      —. Minha Vida e Minhas Idéas 1931
      —. Minha Infância e Mocidade, Histórias Africanas ?
      —. Het Licht in Ons (2 copies) 1950
      —. Genie der Menschlichkeit 1957
      —. De mi Infancia y Juventud 1954
      —. Etudes et Temoignages 1952
      —. Out of My Life and Thought (in Japanese) 1939?
      —. Een Pelikan vertelt 1980
      —. Paix ou Guerre atomique 1958
      —. Goethe: der Mensch and das Werk 1949
      —. Goethe 1950
      —. Afrikanische Geschichten 1956
      —. Fra min Barndom og Ungdom 1952
      —. ¿Por qué premio Nóbel de la Paz? 1958
      —. Glaube, ed. R. Brüllmann 1982
      —. The Living Word, Dynamic Maturity Mar., 1966
      —. Your Second Job, Reader's Digest (2 copies) Oct., 1949
      Albert Schweitzer and Anna Wildikann, Eine Pelikan erzählt aus seinem Leben 1950
      —. En Pelikan forteller fra sitt Liv 1954
      Susan Hampshire, Susan's Story 1983
      George L. Hunt, Ten Makers of Modern Protestant Thought, 1958
      Hans Walter Bähr, ed., Albert Schweitzer, (German) 1966
      Hans Margolius, System der Ethik (2 copies) 1967
      —. Werte und Wege 1977
      —. Gedanken; Thoughts 1964
      C. F. Andrews, Was ich Christus verdanke 1947
      Meno Spann and C. R. Goedsche, Deutsch Denker und Forscher 1954
      Anita Daniel, Albert Schweitzer 1963
      Sevald Simonsen, Legen i Urskogen: Albert Schweitzer (2 copies) 1950?, 1955
      Greta Lagerfelt, ed., Fyrbåken i Irskogen: Albert Schweitzer i Lambarene (2 copies) 1925-1950, 1950
      Johann Joseph Fuchs, Die Lehre vom Kontrapunt 1938
      Hermann Baur, "Für oder gegen Albert Schweitzer" [offprint from Hippokrates, vol. 23 1962
      —. Albert Schweitzer: a Clarification (ET of above article) 1962
      Yosuf Karsh, "Albert Schweitzer", Reader's Digest July, 1958
      Emory S. Bogardus, "Albert Schweitzer as a Leader", Sociology and Social Research 1957
      Noel Gillespie, "With Schweitzer in Lambarene', Wisconsin Magazine of History Spring 1971
      Louise Jilek-Aall, Call Mama Doctor: African Notes of a Young Woman Doctor 1979
      LeGette Blythe, Mountain Doctor [E. Gaine Cannon] 1964
      Leopold Wech, ed., Albert Schweitzer: Fackeltrager der Menschlichkeit 1959
      Rhena Schweitzer Miller, "Albert Schweitzer and His Nuclear Concerns Seen Today, Syracuse University Library Associates Courier, Fall, 1986 (offprint)
      Fritz Wartenweiler, Der Urwald Doktor: Albert Schweitzer, ?
      Harald Tigerström, En Brevskrivartrio 1986
      Charles Joy and Melvin Arnold, Albert Schweitzer (Indonesian translation) ?
      Robert Blum, Offrande au Docteur Schweitzer; Poémes 1955
      Rudolf Grabs, Albert Schweitzer: Weg und Werk eines Menschenfreundes 1954
      M. L. R. O'Hara, Handbook of Ethics ?
      Alfred Stucki, Albert Schweitzer: ein Christ der Tat 1954
      Wijsheid uit het Oerwoud (day book with Schweitzer quotations) ?
      Georges Marschal, Un Témoin un Ami 1982
      —. Essais sur le fait religieux 1954
      Georges Marschal and Henry Babel, L'Homme et la Foi 1957
      Peter Lotar, Vom Sinn des Lebens: Ein Gesprach 1951
      Lieselotte Hoffman, Ihr Herz schlug für das Tier 1958
      Joseph Gollomb, Albert Schweitzer: Genius in der Wildness 1957
      Emory Ross, African Heritage 1952
      Fritz Buri, Albert Schweitzer und unsere Zeit 1947
      Johan B. Hygen, Albert Schweitzers Tanker om Kulturen 1954
      Sondra George, Oganga, (unpublished playscript) 1965?
      Carl Stiefl, Doctor Schweitzer: a Life for the Younger Reader (unpublished typescript) 1988
      About Albert Schweitzer (3 Reader's Digest articles) (2 copies) 1956
      Die Zeichen der Zeit, heft 7 1956
      Meddelanden från Professor Albert Schweitzers Verksamhet: XI-XIV (1935-38), XVI-XVIII (1940-44), XX-XXV (1947-57)
      Scrapbook re: Schweitzer film, letters, clippings 1957
      German brochures on books by and about A. S.
      Boston Symphony Orchestra program, 1950-51 season
      Brochures and pamphlets